Faisal Raza

Full Stack Developer / Data Analyst / Data Scientist / Databases

PROFESSIONAL PROFILE

A seasoned Data Web Developer having 7+ years of strong practical experience in Programming, Data Analysis, Data Science, Databases development & management, and Web Development. Possesses excellent IT skills with advanced knowledge in Python, Django framework, Django Rest Framework, HTML, CSS, JavaScript, React JS, JQuery and SQL, Django REST Framework, and Machine Learning Algorithms implementation with Python and R (Logistic Regression, Linear Regression, Random Forest, Decision Tree, Support Vector Machine, KNN and Artificial Neural Networks.

The knack for collecting, organizing, interpreting and reporting data to people who need to make important decisions using strong analytical and problem-solving skills.

Exceptional communication and presentation skills with an emphasis on teamwork, innovation and integrity.

Able to work well both independently and as a part of a productive team, demonstrating the motivation and multi-tasking abilities required to meet demanding deadlines, whilst maintaining the highest of standards.

AREAS OF EXPERTISE

Web Applications, Web API, Databases (PostgreSQL, SQL, mySQL), Data Analysis, Data Visualization (Power BI), Database design & management, Machine Learning, Deep Learning, Strong Programming skills, Problem Solving and Trouble Shooting, Attention to Detail, Time Management, Interpersonal Skills, Leadership, Self-Initiative, Team Management, Result-Driven, Work Under Pressure, Deadline Oriented. Also, can use R Language.

⇒ Self-motivated: Learning new technologies with the help of online courses, and projects. Passionate about processes, people & technology.

Availability: Immediate

Skills:

Python, R, Django, Django Rest Framework, Web Applications, Restful APIs, HTML, CSS, JavaScript, React JS, Pandas, Numpy, Matplotlib, Data Analysis, Data Preprocessing, Data Visualization, Power BI, Machine Learning Algorithms, Deep Learning, SQL, MySQL, PostgreSQL.

Basic knowledge of Apache Airflow and Azure.

Also having good knowledge of Data Structure, Algorithms, distributed systems and software development life cycles.

Ability to complete the project starting from Data gathering till the development phase.

Ability to work remotely.



Nottingham



Education

MSc Data Analytics
University of
Huddersfield (United
Kingdom) With
Distinction

MS Software Engineering Iqra University Islamabad (Pakistan)

BS (HONS) Computer Science IBMS Agriculture University of Peshawar (Pakistan)

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Web Developer | RF Mask Consultants. CANADA | 2019-2021

- Writing efficient code using best practices for software development.
- Working with different web APIs
- Working with REST APIs
- REST Framework
- Working with Object oriented designs and programming
- Creating websites using different languages such as HTML and CSS, React JS
- Working with programmers and Web Designers to create a website that matches the visual design intent.
- Communicating with business colleagues to gather and refine requirements and specifications for content development within agreed-upon timelines.
- Researching a variety of software programs
- Creating and maintaining the documentation for software used
- Improving and enhancing websites after they have been created.
- Developing contingency plans in the event of websites going down.
- Worked on various E-Commerce projects as a web developer using Front-end technologies like HTML, CSS, jQuery, Javascript, React JS and Bootstrap and backend using Python Django.
- Implemented multiple web applications using Django Framework.
- Designed websites using (HTML, CSS, JavaScript, React JS, jQuery, and Bootstrap).
- Maintained effective communication with clients through various reporting and data-gathering stages.

Database Administrator / Web developer | Techlogix, Islamabad, Pakistan | 2014-2019

- Design effective, dependable & reliable databases
- Improve and maintain existing systems
- Tests and database modifications in response to requests
- Address database usage issues and flaws
- Communicate with team members to enhance applications and create best practices.
- Compile user needs and identify new features.
- Create technical and instruction manuals
- Provide data management support to users
- Ensure all database programs meet company and performance requirements
- Research and suggest new database products, services and protocols
- Discussing clients' requirements and proposed solutions.
- Implementing new designs
- Using development tools to write and test code to develop solutions
- Applying off-page SEO (Search Engine Optimisation)
- Managing and uploading website contents

Team Leader / Data Handling / Operations | FedEx UAE/AFG| 2011-2014

- Oversee international and Domestic flight planning.
- Daily Reporting to Head office.

- Generating reports and statistics on a daily, weekly and monthly basis
- Handling Pre and Post alerts
- Handling Team daily operations.

Experience Related Data Analytics:

Experience with MongoDB, MySQL and PostgreSQL

ACADEMIC/ PERSONAL PROJECTS: -

MSC Final Project (Quantifiable Achievement)

Topic (Analysis of behavioral patterns to optimize energy efficiency in smart buildings).

- Language (Python)
- Dashboard (Power BI)
- Research Study (Identify features that affect energy)
- Designed and implemented a Dashboard that displayed the following feature effects on energy consumption
- ASHRAE Dataset
- Statistical Analysis of different features affecting energy consumption (Python)
- Machine Learning (Prediction) using the following estimators:
 - o Random Forest Regressor
 - o Decision Tree Regressor
 - o Support Vector Regressor

Data Analysis & Statistics:

Customer Personality Analysis using Python used Spearman and Pearson Correlation, used One Way and Two-Way ANOVA for Hypothesis Testing. Predictive Analysis for Targeted Advertisement.

Data Mining:

Used R Programming for Predictive Analysis using Heart Dataset used Principal Component Analysis for dimension reduction, and Artificial Neural Network using different Layers and neurons were used for comparative analysis.

Big Data Analytics:

Natural Language Processing using Python, used Kindle Review Dataset, Machine Learning Algorithms Multinomial Naïve Bayes, Logistic Regression and Random Forest were used.

Databases For Big Data: Worked on Railway Reservation System, Car Renting System case study with PostgreSQL & MongoDB.

Data Visualization:

Built an Interactive visualization dashboard on Starbucks Review Analysis using R, dashboard.

Machine Learning:

Used ARIMA, and LSTM models to predict Apple Stock Price with high accuracy. Predicted and compared various supervised ML models using Kaggle Heart Failure Prediction Dataset. Performed Feature extraction and predicted Covid status using KNN with an accuracy of 93%.